原视频名：Why This Rocket Went Sideways Off The Launch Pad
原作者名：Scott Manley
视频来源：youtu.be/x2jU5W4ehPE
原视频发布日期：20210829
字幕翻译：旋火
Hello, it's Scott Manley here.
你好 我是Scott Manley
Today, Astra launched their sixth rocket
今天 阿斯特拉发射了他们的第六枚火箭
hoping to finally demonstrate their ability to reach a stable orbit.
希望最终能验证他们到达稳定轨道的能力
This launch, instead that has become one of the more memorable launches of recent times
这次发射 反而成了近期最令人难忘的发射之一
or all time, to be honest.
或者说实话 是一直以来
The rocket lost one of five engines almost immediately
火箭几乎立即失去了五台发动机中的一台
and with a thrust weight ratio of 1,
而且在推重比为1的情况下
it pretty much went sideways, hovering slaughterly across the landscape
它几乎是侧着在飞 盘旋着摧毁着美丽的风景
until it eventually burned enough propellant to start heading upwards.
直到它最终燃烧了足够的推进剂 开始往上飞
And I'm going to say right away,
而我要马上说的是
I have a huge amount of respect for Astras guidance and navigation team,
我对阿斯特拉的制导和导航团队充满了敬意
because that rocket, it kept control.
因为那枚火箭 它保持了控制
It didn't have enough thrust.
其推力并不足够
It had asymmetric thrust.
其推力并不对称
But it kept moving and it kept going up, which makes this next call out amazing.
但它一直在移动 一直在上升 这使得接下来的呼号令人惊讶
Our next objective is Max-Q.
我们的下一个目标是最大气动压力(Max-Q)
Yeah, I mean, they just let that thing go,
是的 我的意思是 他们只是放着让那火箭飞
and there's a good reason for that,
而这是有原因的
because this rocket if they had just terminated the flight,
因为这枚火箭如果刚刚终止了飞行
it would have fallen back inside the missile range.
它就会落回(安全)射程内
And that would have been an expensive cleanup operation.
而这就意味着要进行一次昂贵的清理行动
They previously had a couple of failures, which required expensive environmental cleanup.
他们之前有几次失败 需要昂贵的环境清理
So by letting the thing continue, they had a good chance of getting out to see
因此 通过让发射继续下去 火箭才有机会离开发射场 并弄清发生的事情
that was the sort of first objective.
而这是第一个目标
The next objective was how far can it fly, so they can collect engineering data.
下一个目标是它能飞多远 以便他们能收集工程数据
I mean, it was pretty clear to us watching that it wasn't going to reach orbit.
我的意思是 对我们来说 很清楚它不可能到达轨道
Its ascent was too slow.
它的上升速度太慢了
We didn't know initially that it had lost an engine,
我们最初并不知道它失去了一台发动机
but we did see that it didn't have enough thrust.
但我们确实看到它没有足够的推力
And that meant that it was wasting a lot of its Delta V fighting against gravity.
而这意味着它浪费了大量的速度增量(dv)与重力对抗
And only slowly beginning to hit really decent speeds.
而且只是慢慢地开始达到真正可接受的速度
So it cleared the island about a minute and a half into the flight,
那么它在飞行了大约一分半钟的时间后就离开了这个岛
but it was still at subsonic at this point.
但在此时 它仍处于亚音速状态
Normally, it would have past Max-Q at about one minute and fifteen seconds,
通常情况下 它将在大约1分15秒时通过Max-Q
and the total engine burn would be two minutes and fifty seconds.
而发动机的总燃烧时间为2分50秒
We had to actually guess at most of this telemetry, it only came up later in the flight.
我们实际上不得不猜测这些遥测数据的大部分 它只是在飞行后期才出现的
In fact, the telemetry early on showed negative velocity, which is not something you want to see.
事实上 早期的遥测数据显示了负的速度 这不是你想看到的东西
But yeah, the two minute mark
但是 是的 在两分钟的时候
we start to actually see some real views back to the the launch site down there.
我们开始真正看到一些看回下方发射场的真实景象
Astra launches from the Pacific Spaceport Complex on Kodiak Island in Alaska.
阿斯特拉火箭从阿拉斯加科迪亚克岛的太平洋太空港综合体发射
Anyway this camera is looking down to the side of the rocket
无论如何 这台相机正俯视着火箭的侧面
and it's about to cut its engines,
而它正准备关闭它的发动机
but if you look on the right side, you can see a piece sticking out.
但如果你看右边 可以看到有一块东西伸出来
That is part of the aerodynamic cover for the cable raceway,
那是线缆通道的整流罩的一部分
and when we cut the engines, that gets pulled out, and you get a better idea.
而在关闭发动机时 它就会被拉出来 这样就看得更清楚了
But yet, the Astra launch vehicle, its flight termination system basically involves cutting the engines
但是 阿斯特拉运载火箭 它的飞行终止系统基本上包括关闭发动机
and letting it fall into the ocean and that's what they did.
并让它落入海洋 而这就是他们所做的
And you can see that this vehicle instantly spends out of control due to the aerodynamic forces,
你可以看到 由于空气动力的作用 这个火箭瞬间就失去了控制
even although that is 36 kilometers up, that's over 100000 feet.
尽管那是在36公里的高空 也就是超过10万英尺
I did the math based on the telemetry,
我根据遥测数据做了计算
and it looks like it was moving upwards, at 150 meters per second
看起来它是以每秒150米的速度向上移动的
and sideways or down range at 600 meters per second.
并以每秒600米的速度向侧方或(弹道)下方(水平方向)移动
So it looks based on the telemetry,
所以根据遥测数据看来
that it probably plateaus or apogees at about 47 kilometers, a long way from space.
它可能在约47公里处达到最高点或远地点 而这里离太空还很远
And then would fall into the ocean a several minutes later.
然后将在几分钟后落入海洋
And while they did cut away from the onboard camera, showing it spinning out of control,
虽然他们确实切掉了显示火箭失控旋转的箭载相机的镜头
they did cut back to the ground camera
但是他们确实切回了地面相机
which does a marvelous job of showing the field that it is just plowed.
而这很好地展示了刚才被火箭毁坏过的土地
I mean, I guess it's a good thing they kept the gate open right.
我的意思是 我想这是一件好事 他们保持了开放的心态
And so, really, while this is spectacular and will be talked about for a very long time,
那么 真的 虽然这很壮观 而且会被谈论很长时间
it isn't a good result for Astra, and I really feel sorry for them.
这对阿斯特拉来说不是一个好结果 我真的为他们感到遗憾
They've been working on this project for a long time.
他们已经在这个项目上工作了很长时间
They've iterated on their rocket a great deal.
他们已经对他们的火箭进行了大量的迭代
This was another variant of their model 3 or version 3 rocket.
这是他们的第3型号或者说第3版本火箭的另一个变种
One of the main things that they changed was
他们改变的主要内容之一是
that they had extended the first stage by about 5 more feet to add more propellant.
把一级延长了大约1.5米 以增加推进剂
And this extra propellent was in part to make up for the fact that
而这一额外的推进剂部分是为了弥补以下的事实
last December and their launch number 5, they had got through their first stage.
去年12月 他们的第5次发射 一级工作正常
They'd separate the second stage, and it had got incredibly close to being in orbit.
一二级分离也正常 而且它已经令人难以置信地接近于入轨
They come up short by less than 500 meters per second which
但最后只差了不到500米/秒的速度
is essentially orbital velocity when you hit the atmosphere at that speed,
当你以这个速度进入大气层时 基本上是轨道速度(的热量)
but unfortunately, it doesn't keep you in orbit.
但不幸的是 它并不能使你保持在轨道上
And so Astra were making a big deal about how this launch would be the one to show that
因此阿斯特拉大肆宣扬这次的发射是要表明
they were able to do what they promised
他们能够兑现承诺
and it's getting more important
而且兑现承诺这件事现在变得更加重要
because they are now a publicly traded company, and people own stock in Astra.
因为阿斯特拉现在是一家上市公司 人们拥有它的股票
And that has given the company more money to play with.
而上市给了这家公司更多的钱来花费
And when Chris Kemp came up afterwards to explain, or give the concession Speech
当克里斯·坎普(阿斯特拉CEO)事后解释 或者说发表失败讲话时
he pointed out this is Booster number 7, sitting behind him, ready to go
他指出他身后的是7号助推器 随时准备出发
as soon as they figure out exactly what went wrong on this flight.
只要他们搞清楚这次飞行到底出了什么问题
And most of the interesting stuff happens in the first few seconds.
而大部分有趣的事情都发生在前几秒钟
So one thing to watch is the very bottom of the rocket on the right side.
所以要注意的是火箭右侧的最底部
You will see the raceway cover get kicked up by some event and bang into the site.
你会看到通道整流罩被不明的事件掀起 并撞向地面
That's the thing that we see flapping in that camera.
这就是我们在之前那个镜头中看到的拍打的东西
Then the vehicle moves up a little, pitches over sideways
然后 火箭向上移动了一点 向侧方倾斜
and immediately the vehicle tries to correct itself,
然后其立即试图纠正姿态
but of course it's moving laterally, so it just puts itself vertically upwards.
但当然它是倾斜地移动的 所以这样的纠正只是让姿态垂直
At this point, it is burning propellent and getting lighter and lighter,
在此时 它正在燃烧推进剂 变得越来越轻
and it begins to move upwards, ever so slowly.
然后开始非常缓慢地向上移动
And of course that lateral motion is somewhat different from regular rocket launches.
当然 这种横向运动与普通的火箭发射有些不同
I mean, we all know that rockets spend most of their time picking up horizontal speeds
我的意思是 我们都知道 火箭花了大部分时间来提高水平速度
so they can stay in orbit.
所以它们可以留在轨道上
In this case, the Astra just tried to do it a little early.
在这种情况下 阿斯特拉号只是试图早一点完成它
Anyway, if you look at that panel popping out,
总之 如果你看一下那个弹出的面板
you'll notice there is a flash of an explosion that pushes that out,
你会发现有一个爆炸的闪光 把它推了出来
so there's like an explosion of some sort.
那么看起来是发生了某种爆炸
That's probably related to the engine shutting down prematurely.
这可能与发动机过早的关闭有关
And you can also see at this point that
你还可以看到 在此时
the rocket has actually started moving upwards when this event happens.
当这个事件发生时 火箭实际上已经开始向上移动
So with one of the engines going out, it's not getting enough thrust on one side,
所以随着一台发动机的熄灭 它的一侧没有得到足够的推力
and it starts to pitch over in one direction.
之后开始向一个方向倾斜
So immediately, of course, the computer on board
因此 当然 箭上的计算机立即
does the whole flaming end thing down and pointy end up
将喷火的一端下压 而尖尖的一端竖起
but it's still moving latterly.
但它仍在向后移动
Quickly disappearing into a cloud of steam, rather like Homer Simpson disappearing into a hedge.
迅速消失在一团蒸汽中 就像霍默·辛普森消失在树篱里一样
Now the steam kind of hides what's going on down there,
那么 蒸汽有点掩盖了下面发生的事情
but there's a few frames where the engines peek out,
但有几帧是能看到微微露出的发动机的
and you can see a gap there in them.
而你可以看到它们之间有一个缺口
Having said that I wouldn't read too much into that,
说了这么多 我也不会对这一点看得太重
because this image by John Kraus shows that there is a visible gaps depending upon the angle.
因为John Kraus的这张图片显示 在某些角度下 能看到明显的缝隙
The nozzles are quite far apart.
喷嘴之间的距离相当远
Also, the images where we've seen gaps don't quite line up where we would expect the engine that failed to be.
此外 图片中的缝隙并不完全符合我们所期望的失败的发动机的位置
Astra, CEO, Chris Kemp posted the other angle on to Twitter video,
阿斯特拉的CEO克里斯·坎普在推特上发布了另一个角度的视频
and of course Twitter video is lousy in terms of quality.
当然 推特的视频画质很渣
But it is another angle, and there's a couple of things to see.
但这是另一个角度 有几件事情要看
From this angle, you don't get to see the panel popping up,
从这个角度看 你没有看到面板弹出的情况
but you do get to see a flash in the engine's root area.
但你确实可以看到发动机根部的闪光
And as the rocket turns over,
当火箭翻转时
you get to see the engines just running through the bottom of launch stand and throwing debris out.
你可以看到发动机的尾焰刚刚穿过发射台的底部 把碎片扔了出去
This view does give us a slightly better look at the launch clamp as it pops backwards to release the rocket.
这个视角看确实更方便看到发射台支撑臂向后弹出以释放火箭的过程
And once that booster starts moving, it's absolutely in their best interest
而一旦助推器开始移动 最好就是
to try and keep it moving as far away from the launch site as possible.
试图让它尽可能地远离发射场
And usually that means going upwards rather than sideways.
而这通常意味着要向上走 而不是向侧面走
So anyway the other bit to watch in slow motion is the end of the flight after they've shut off the engines,
因此 无论如何 需要慢动作观看的另一个部分是发动机关闭后飞行结束的那部分
and you can get a better idea of the shape of that object, which is attached there.
而你可以更好地了解贴在那里的那个物体的形状
And just dangling around, right. You can see that it's actually hollow.
而它就这样悬空着 对吧 你可以看到 它实际上是空心的
So anyway, this is an image of the older version of 3.0 rocket slightly shorter,
那么无论如何 这是一张老版本3.0火箭的照片 稍短一些
but the base of is what I care about.
但我关心的是它的底座
You can see on the rocket going up, there's a raceway, which had the cables and other stuff.
你可以看到在火箭上升的过程中 有一个包含电缆和其他东西的通道
You'll also see that there's like fuel lines running into that.
你还会看到 有像燃料管线一样的东西塞在里面
You can see five engines, and I think that engine in the middle closest to us, that's the one that went out.
你可以看到五台发动机 我想中间离我们最近的那台发动机 就是出问题的那个
Because when the rocket started to veer off, it basically came towards the camera angle here.
因为当火箭开始偏离时 它基本上是朝着相机的角度来的
And in this photo, you can see that there are actually what looks like fluid lines,
在这张照片中 你可以看到 实际上有一些看起来像液体管道的东西
possibly propellent lines running into that.
可能那就是推进剂的管线
And you could imagine, if there was some sort of blast in there,
而你可以想象 如果那里发生了某种爆炸
that debris could come from that and hit that motor at the top
碎片可能来自于此并击中顶部的发动机
damaging the nozzle and possibly causing the engine to shut down, pretty much straight away.
损坏喷嘴 可能导致发动机几乎是立刻关闭
So the rocket had a thrust-to-weight ratio of 1.25, and as soon as it lost an engine, it was down to 1.
因此 火箭的推重比为1.25 一旦它失去了一台发动机 就会下降到1
And it was just basically trying to keep itself from falling over and destroying anything critical.
而且它基本上只是试图保持自己不倒下 不破坏任何关键的东西
It ascended slowly, picked up speed,
它缓慢上升 加快了速度
but basically it was burning too much propellent and not getting enough accel.
但基本上它燃烧了太多的推进剂而没有得到足够的加速
It was losing too much energy to gravity losses.
它因重力损失而损失了太多的能量
And of course that meant that Max-Q happened way later.
当然 这也意味着Max-Q发生得很晚
Main engine cut out was supposed to be at two minutes, fifty seconds,
主发动机关机的时间应该是2分50秒
but because it was running on only four engines rather than five,
但由于它只靠四台发动机而不是五台发动机运行
it would have had an extra thirty seconds or so before it ran out propellent.
所以一级工作的时间多出了30秒
But they called the flight termination early,
但他们提前宣布了飞行终止
and I think the reason they called the flight termination before MECO
而我想他们之所以在一级发动机关闭之前宣布终止飞行
was that they wanted to make sure that the booster fell into this first exclusion zone.
是他们想确保助推器落入这个第一禁区
They wanted to keep it flying long enough they wouldn't land on the island.
他们想让它飞行足够长的时间 这样不会在岛上降落
I think they were happy to get some flight time on it to verify other systems,
我认为他们很高兴得到一些飞行时间来验证其他系统
but if they let it run too long, it would have probably ended up between those two zones,
但如果让火箭运行得太久 就可能会在这两个禁区之间掉落
and that would have caused a bit of a consternation with the FAA.
而这将引起美国联邦航空管理局(FAA)的不安
And one thing I haven't mentioned is that this is Astra's first proper, like livestream launch.
还有一件事 这是阿斯特拉的第一次正式的现场直播的发射
And they actually did it in collaboration with NASASpaceflight.com,
而且他们实际上是与NASASpaceflight.com(NSF)合作进行的
who essentially, a bunch of hardcore rocket fans who do this semi-professionally.
NSF 基本上是一群铁杆火箭迷 他们半职业地做这件事
And I think it was a really good stream,
而且我认为这是一个非常好的直播
I'm really happy that Astra opened up and started sharing this with the world,
我真的很高兴阿斯特拉抱着开放的心态并开始与世界分享发射过程
and it is a hurt that they did this and they were rewarded with a failure.
但是这样直播却遭到了失败实在让人痛心
I really hope this continues,
我真的希望这能继续下去
because I thought it was actually a pretty well produced stream,
因为我认为这实际上是一次精心准备的直播
and unfortunately the hardware was left wanting.
但不幸的是 设备方面却不尽如人意
and I hope that Astra get through the engineering problems, they solve it,
而我希望阿斯特拉能解决工程上的问题
and a few years from now they can look back on this absurd. Initial launch and and laugh,
而在几年后 他们可以回顾一下这个荒谬的 最初的发射 然后大笑
because I think people will remember this for a long time.
因为我认为人们会在很长一段时间内记住这件事
And I hope that Astra remembered for more than the people that launched the rocket sideways.
而且我希望人们能记得阿斯特拉不仅仅那个是把火箭侧向发射的公司
I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.
我是Scott Manley 切记 注意飞行安全